Guide to the Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington Correspondence
1847-1927
GEN MSS 215
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.13
3 boxes
Autograph manuscript letters, signed, of Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington and their correspondents. Letters concern: casting of theatrical productions; investing in theatrical projects; Charrington's involvement in the Fabian Society; and other professional and domestic topics. Correspondents include Harley Granville-Barker, William Poel, and Kate Santley. Also included is a booking sheet for the Vaudeville Theatre, London, circa 1880.
Achurch, Janet, 1863-1916
Charrington, Charles
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James M. Osborn, 1951, and Mark Samuels Lasner, 2016.
Biographical / Historical
Janet Achurch (1863-1916) was an English actress and actor-manager. She was noted for her role as Nora in an 1889 production of Henrik Ibsen's A Doll's House in London, produced by her husband, the actor-manager Charles Charrington.
Charles Charrington (1854-1926) was an English actor-manager and member of the Fabian Society.
Scope and Contents
Autograph manuscript letters, signed, of Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington and their correspondents. Letters concern: casting of theatrical productions; investing in theatrical projects; Charrington's involvement in the Fabian Society; and other professional and domestic topics. Correspondents include George Henry Boughton, Stopford Augustus Brooke, Charles H. E. Brookfield, Harley Granville-Barker, St. John Emile Clavering Hankin, Henry Holiday, Gertrude Kingston, May Morris, Felix Moscheles, William Poel, Charles Rock, Kate Santley, Clement Scott, William Sharp, Arthur Streeton, Julian Sturgis, Fred Terry, John Todhunter, Hermann Vezin, Mrs. Humphry Ward, and Sir Frederick Wedmore, and unidentified. Also included is a booking sheet for the Vaudeville Theatre, London, circa 1880.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. James M. Osborn Gift, 1887-1900. II. Mark Samuels Lasner Gift, 1847-1927.
Actors -- England; Theater -- England; Theatrical producers and directors -- England; Actors -- England -- 19th century; Theatrical producers and directors -- England; Achurch, Janet, 1863-1916; Boughton, George Henry, 1834-1905; Brooke, Stopford A. (Stopford Augustus), 1832-1916; Brookfield, Charles H. E. (Charles Hallam Elton), 1857-1913; Charrington, Charles; Granville-Barker, Harley, 1877-1946; Hankin, St. John, 1869-1909; Holiday, Henry, 1839-1927; Kingston, Gertrude, 1866-1937; Morris, May, 1862-1938; Moscheles, Felix, 1833-1917; Poel, William, 1852-1934; Rock, Charles, 1866-1919; Santley, Kate; Scott, Clement, 1841-1904; Sharp, William, 1855-1905; Streeton, Arthur, Sir, 1867-1943; Sturgis, Julian, 1848-1904; Terry, Fred, 1863-1933; Todhunter, John, 1839-1916; Vezin, Hermann, 1829-1910; Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920; Wedmore, Frederick, Sir, 1844-1921; Fabian Society (Great Britain)
- Series I. James M. Osborn Gift, 1887–1900; 0.20; 1 box
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes correspondence of Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington.
  - Achurch, Janet to "Vera", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boughton, George Henry, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooke, Stopford Augustus, 1893 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brookfield, Charles Hallam Elton, 1889–1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charrington, Charles, from various unidentified correspondents, 1889–1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Granville-Barker, Harley, no year February 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hankin, St. John Emile Clavering, no year July 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Holiday, Henry, 1900 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kingston, Gertrude, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Morris, May, 1893 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Moscheles, Felix, 1900 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poel, William, 1900 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rock, Charles, 1900 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Santley, Kate, 1897; 1899 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scott, William Clement, 1887 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sharp, William, 1900 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Streeton, Arthur, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sturgis, Julian, no year February 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Terry, Fred, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Todhunter, John, 1892 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Vezin, Hermann, 1889; 1900 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ward, Mary Augusta, 1893 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Wedmore, Sir Frederick, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series II. Mark Samuels Lasner Gift, 1847–1927; 1.92; 2 boxes
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent within subseries for Achurch and Charrington, followed by third-party, unrelated, and unidentified correspondence, and the booking sheet for the Vaudeville Theatre, London.
  Series II includes correspondence of Janet Achurch and Charles Charrington from identified and unidentified correspondents. Also included is third-party correspondence, letters regarding theatrical matters but unrelated to Achurch and Charrington, and a booking sheet for the Vaudeville Theatre, London.
  - Janet Achurch Outgoing Correspondence
    - Manager, Mackenzie Typewriter Company, 1894 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Sitwell, Mr., 1894 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Vera", 1894 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Janet Achurch Incoming Correspondence
    - Arkwright, Agnes, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Berry, E. D., 1893 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Bishop, Gwendolyn, no year July 12 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Boord, Margaret, 1893 February 4 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Brooke, Frances Evelyn, 1893; undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Brooke, Maud, 1893 February 4 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Dudley, Rachel, 1893 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Eller, Harry, no year December 21 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Ellis, Fannie M., 1890 August 8 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Farrell, Florence, no year April 11 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Godfrey, J. Perry, 1897 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Hervey, R. K., no year February 22 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Laurence, Hetty, no year June 22 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Morrison, G. E., 1893 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Olivier, Sydney, 1895 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Russell, Edward, 1893 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - [S.?], Isabel, no year May 24 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - [Silver, Gertrude?], Easter Sunday 1894 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - [Sim?], Charles A., no year May 8 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Sitwell, Blanche, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Somerset, Lady Henry, 1893 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - [Stern?], Margaret, no year Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Terry, Fred, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Thompson, [Delle?], no year May 12 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Violet", Sunday (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Wharncliffe, Earl of, 1893 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Willard, Rachel Emily, 1899 August 3 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Young, Mr., no year May 28 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Unidentified, 1887–1896 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Letter fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Charles Charrington Outgoing Correspondence
    - Charrington, Charles and Dorothy Leighton printed circular soliciting donations for the Independent Theatre, 1897 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Charrington, Charles to "Sir", 1900 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Charrington, Charles to unidentified recipient, 1898 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Charles Charrington Incoming Correspondence
    - Armstrong, G. Rose, 1900 April 25 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Barrett, T.S., 1896 November 19 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Bolton, T., 1888 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - [Bond?], Henry, 1896 January 21 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - [Borchard?], S., 1897 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Brandt, Natalie, 1900 May 28; 1900 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Brooke, Eleanor Raffles, 1897 April 23; no year March 9 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Burke, H., Metropolitan Police, 1892? June 15 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Davey, R., undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Davies, John, 1898 July 19 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Dawson, Arthur, 1899 October 12; 1899 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Day, [?], 1893 June 21; 1897 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Fallows, Arthur, no year July 12 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Galton, F. W., 1900 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - George, A. E., 1900 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Green, J. Frederick, 1900 January 29 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Green Room Club, 1893 April 3 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Greet, Ben, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Grein, J.T., 1900 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Groves, Fred, no year May 10 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Henderson, Laura, no year July 14 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Hervey, R. K., no year June 6 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Horder, P. Morley, 1893 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Howard Wyndham Ltd, 1897 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Howard, J. Bannister, 1897 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Iver, Frances, undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Johnson, F., no year January 3 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Kingston, Gertrude S., 1893 April 26; no year February 7 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Knollys, Francis, 1893 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Law, Arthur, 1892 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Leattridge, Julia, 1900 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Lewis, Eric, 1900 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Mallett, Charles S., 1892 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Martin, "Aunt Mary", 1896 October 22; 1900 July 31 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Matesdorf, T., 1899 July 19; 1900 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Matheson, L., 1893 June 1; 1893 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Maxwell, [?], no year May 28 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Mond, Ludwig, 1893 March 19 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - [Nevell?], Mary H., undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - [Palmer?], Walter, 1893 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Paternoster, G. Sidney, 1900 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - [Pearl?], Emma, 1896 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - [Phifer, Sidney?], undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Philipps, Nora, 1899 July 10 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Revell, Lilian, undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Sachs, Edwin O., 1897 February 26 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Sala, Ida, 1893 April 7 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Santley, Kate, 1893 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Sassoon, Albert, 1893 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Simonds, R., 1896 February 13 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Smith, Thomas F., no year October 31 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Sprange, Jo. H., 1892 August 29 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Stacey, A., 1893 August 27 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Tennant, Gertrude, 1892 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Terrell, James, 1896 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Thompson, H. O., 1899 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Turner, George, 1898 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Vayne, Gwennie, undated (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Wallis, Lena, 1900 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Warden, Sidney, no year February 5 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Westmacott, [R.J.?], 1895 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Wheeler, Ethel M. D., 1899 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - [Wilkins?], Nancy, no year February 24 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Williams, Ernest E. S., 1900 August 28 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Wyn, Alfred E., 1900 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Unidentified, 1889–1900 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Third party and unrelated correspondence
    - Aberdeen, Lord and Lady, 1911–1933; undated (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Kelly, W. W., 1892 August 25 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Raffin, Mr., 1927–1929; undated (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Julia Neilson and Fred Terry, 1913; 1925; undated (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Unidentified, 1847; 1899; undated (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Booking sheet for Vaudeville Theatre, London, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 131)